can be done end of Chapter 16
[Music]
this is a librivox recording all librivox recordings are in the public
domain for more information or to volunteer please visit librivox.org this recording by jay hall
The Wonderful Wizard of Oz by l frank Baum chapter 17 How the Balloon Was
lodged For three days Dorothy heard nothing from Oz. These were sad days for
the little girl, although her friends were all quite happy and contented. The
Scarecrow told them there were wonderful thoughts in his head; but he would not
say what they were because he knew no one could understand them but himself.
When the Tin Woodman walked about he felt his heart rattling around in his
breast; and he told Dorothy he had discovered it to be a kinder and more
tender heart than the one he had owned when he was made of flesh. The Lion
declared he was afraid of nothing on earth, and would gladly face an army or a
dozen of the fierce collie DAWs Thus each of the little party was satisfied
except Dorothy, who longed more than ever to get back to Kansas. On the fourth day,
to her great joy, Oz sent for her, and when she entered the Throne Room he
greeted her pleasantly: “Sit down, my dear; I think I have found a way to get you
out of this country.” “And back to Kansas?” she asked eagerly.
“Well, I’m not sure about Kansas,” said Oz, “for I haven’t the faintest notion which
way it lies. But the first thing to do is to cross the desert, and then it should
be easy to find your way home.” “How can I cross the desert?” she inquired. “Well, I’ll
tell you what I think,” said the little man. “You see, when I came to this country
it was in a balloon. You also came through the air, being carried by a
cyclone. So I believe the best way to get across the desert will be through the
air. Now, it is quite beyond my powers to make a cyclone; but I’ve been thinking
the matter over, and I believe I can make a balloon.” “How?” asked Dorothy.
“A balloon,” said Oz, “is made of silk, which is coated with glue to keep the gas in
it. I have plenty of silk in the Palace, so it will be no trouble to make the
balloon. But in all this country there is no gas to fill the balloon with, to make
it float.” “If it won’t float,” remarked Dorothy, “it will be of no use to us.”
“True,” answered Oz. “But there is another way to make it float, which is to fill it
with hot air. Hot air isn’t as good as
gas, for if the air should get called the balloon would come down in the desert,
and we should be lost.” “We exclaim the girl. “Are you going with
me?” “Yes, of course,” replied Oz. “I am tired of being such a humbug. If I should go
out of this Palace my people would soon discover I am not a Wizard, and then they
would be vexed with me for having deceived them. So I have to stay shut up
in these rooms all day, and it gets tiresome. I’d much rather go back to
Kansas with you and being a circus again.” “I should be glad to have your company,”
said Dorothy. “Thank you,” he answered. “Now, if you will help me sew
the silk together, we will begin work on our balloon.” So Dorothy took a needle and
thread, and as fast as Oz cut the strips of silk into proper shape the girl sewed
them neatly together. First there was a strip of light green silk, then a strip
of dark green and then a strip of emerald green; for Oz had a fancy to make
the balloon in different shades of the color about them. It took three days to
sew all the strip's together, but when it was finished they had a big bag of green
silk more than 20 feet long.
Then Oz painted it on the inside with a coat of thin glue, to make it airtight,
after which he announced that the balloon was ready. “But we must have a
basket to ride in,” he said. So he sent the soldier with the green whiskers for a
big clothes basket, which he fashioned with many ropes to the bottom of the
balloon. When it was all ready, Oz sent word to his people that he was going to
make a visit to a great brother Wizard who lived in the clouds. The news spread
rapidly throughout the city and everyone came to see the wonderful sight. Oz
ordered the balloon carried out in front of the Palace, and the people gazed upon
it with much curiosity. The Tin Woodman had chopped a big pie
would and now he made a fire of it, and Oz held the bottom of the balloon over
the fire so that the hot air that rose from it would be caught in the silken
bag. Gradually the balloon swelled out and rose into the air, until finally the
basket just touched the ground. Then Oz got into the basket and said to all the
people in a loud voice: “I am now going away to make a visit. While I am gone
the Scarecrow will rule over you. I command you to obey him as you would me.”
The balloon was by this time chugging hard at the rope that held it to the
ground, for the air within was hot, and this made it so much lighter in weight
than the air without that it pulled hard to rise into the sky. “Come, Dorothy!” cried
the Wizard. “Hurry up where the balloon will fly away.” “I can’t find Toto anywhere,”
replied Dorothy, who did not wish to leave her little dog behind. Toto had run
into the crowd to bark at a kitten, and Dorothy at last found him. She picked him
up and ran towards the balloon. She was within a few steps of it, and Oz was
holding out his hands to help her into the basket, when clack went the ropes, and
the balloon rose into the air without her. “Come back!” she screamed. “I want to go,
too!” “I can’t come back, my dear,” called woz from the basket goodbye goodbye shout at
everyone, and all eyes were turned upward to where the Wizard was riding in the
basket, rising every moment farther and farther into the sky. And that was the
last any of them ever saw of Oz, the Wonderful Wizard, though he may have
reached Omaha safely, and be there now, for all we know. But the people
remembered him lovingly, and said to one another Yas was always our friend. When he was
here he built for us this beautiful Emerald City, and now he is gone he has
left us the why Scarecrow to rule over us.” Still, for many days they grieved over